

#### **CONTACT ME AT**

- Dubai Marina, Dubai, United Arab Emirates
- talal.absar619@gmail.com
- UAE: +971 50 705 7899 PK: +923362045945

#### PROGRAMMING SKILLS

- Android Development, Kotlin, Java, MVVM, Clean Architecture, Jetpack Compose, XML, Retrofit, Flow, LiveData, Coroutines, Data Binding, Android Jetpack Libraries, Android Jetpack Navigation, Room, Hilt-Dagger, Dependency Injection, Memory Management, REST, SOAP, ISON, NFT, Blockchain, Web3, Smart Contracts, PHP, NodeJS, C#, C, Python, MongoDB, Data Structure and Algorithms, Software Design Patterns, Modular Application Architecture, Software Architectural Patterns, Test Driven Development, SOLID principles, CI/CD, Git, JIRA, Scrum, Agile Methodology, Flat Organizational Structure.
- Flutter Android/IOS Application, Dart, Widgets, Clean code, BLoC Architectural Pattern, Jenkins.

# TALAL ABSAR

# SENIOR LEAD SOFTWARE ENGINEER - ANDROID

#### PERSONAL PROFILE

I am an experienced software engineer with a passion for building smart applications and keen on developing effective and efficient solutions following best practices. A creative and detailed individual, who seeks challenging opportunities whichstimulates my passion for learning.

## **WORK EXPERIENCE**

# Senior Software Engineer-Android | Toggle Market

Dubai, United Arab Emirates | Jan 2020 - Present

Responsible to design and develop the mobile and web applications, Android applications, and MERN for web. Android Kotlin, XML, Android Jetpack Libraries, MVVM, Clean Architecture, Retrofit, Coroutines, Flow, LiveData, Data Binding, Room, Glide, Hilt-Dagger, REST Services, GitHub, Jira. In addition, led the major sections of the mobile and web application where I have worked on search algorithm for products gallery and bill of quantities section for transaction settlement.

# Senior Software Engineer-Android | Network Intelligent Payment Solutions

Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates | July 2016 - Jan 2020

Design and developed android applications for government entities with payment integration using Java, Kotlin, MVVM XML, Room, Retrofit, RxJava, Glide, REST services, SOAP Services, GitHub, Jira.

#### Software Engineer-Android | Wemsol Private Limited

Karachi, Pakistan | June 2014 - July 2016

Developed an internet mobile banking application for Askari Bank and Badlo application (assesses your social, physical and mental health) using Java, XML, Picasso, REST services, GitHub, Jira.

# **EDUCATION**

# Bachelor of Science in Computer Engineering

Sir Syed University of Engineering and Technology 2010 – 2013

#### **GITHUB PROIECTS LINK**

https://github.com/TalalAbsar10

# **PROJECTS**

#### **TOGGLE HOSPITALITY**

Buyers from the hospitality management sector can purchase products from potential suppliers, who sell their own products on the Toggle Hospitality platform.

Role: Senior Software Developer-Android

#### **AUTOGRAPH**

Autograph is a social networking application with multiple registration options from Facebook, Google, and Instagram. Find nearby people using **Beacon (BLE)** technology and Google maps API.

Chat implementation using **XMPP protocols**. Advertisement module, where users view, and purchase offers by online payment.

Profile Management according to the user interest.

Role: Senior Software Developer-Android

# ABU DHABI JUDICIAL DEPARTMENT

Customer can pay fines through a Payment Gateway using different options provided by the Abu Dhabi Judicial Department.

Role: Senior Software Developer-Android

#### **DUBAI TAXI CORPORATION**

Customer can explore application features like paying fines and taxi fare through a payment gateway, watching videos, watching routes on map, news bulletin, weather updates, and many other services.

Role: Senior Software Developer-Android

#### ROAD TRANSPORTATION AUTHORITY DUBAI

Customer can pay their traffic fines, do vehicle license renewal/vehicle loss and damage, driver license renewal/loss and damage, print certificate, and parking services through a payment gateway.

Role: Senior Software Developer-Android

#### ASKARI INTERNET BANKING APPLICATION

Customer can transfer online money to the added beneficiary, pay bills, and see transaction summaries on theapplication.

**Role:** Software Developer-Android

https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.askari

# **BADLO APPLICATION**

Based on the social, mental, and physical health of a person which can improve a person's daily life routine then see the results in a graphical view. User can also listen to daily tips anent to its health and get daily notifications to check on tips and exercises.

Role: Software Developer-Android

https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.badlo.app